Jeevan Patil

Bengaluru, Karnataka 🤳 +91 8446669319 💌 patiljeevanr@gmail.com 🛅 linkedin.com/in/patiljeevanr

SUMMARY

Back-end Developer with almost 5 Years of Experience in Java-based Micro-services delivering High-Quality Solutions.

SKILLS

Languages Java

Cloud Azure, AWS

Database Couchbase, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Redis

Automation Terraform, Azure Pipelines

Data Processing Kafka

Framework Spring, Micronaut

Tools Docker, Kubernetes

Interests Data Structures and Algorithms, Database

RECENT EXPERIENCE

Tesco Technology, Bangalore

Aug 2019 - Present

Software Development Engineer II

- Introduced Cucumber for behavior-driven development and implemented various refinements in the development process and pull request guidelines to ensure smoother collaboration and more efficient code reviews
- Implemented caching mechanism using Couchbase for retrieving customer coupons wallets, reducing latency substantially with higher throughput
- Designed and implemented a Coupon Code Generator tailored to coupon types and business logic, considering various methods of coupon utilization
- Decommissioned the Redis cache due to its high cost, resulting in significant cost savings for Tesco Technologies Used: Java, Couchbase, PostgreSQL

Graduate Software Development Engineer

- With Work focused on moving legacy outdated systems to more strategic systems, involved in building Coupon At Till from scratch for Tesco UK and ROI
- Designed and implemented housekeeping of customers' data, ensuring data integrity and optimal performance
- Developed RESTful APIs to enable the creation, redemption, and viewing functionalities for coupons and vouchers information of customers
- Enhanced the performance of test pipelines, leading to a smoother and more efficient production deployment process
- Conducted extensive load tests for all APIs to ensure the team was fully prepared to handle peak season traffic, which reached approximately 50,000 transactions per second
- Provided on-call support for critical issues and worked on root cause analysis for incident resolution
 Technologies Used: Java, Elixir, node.js, Couchbase, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Redis

CDAC, Pune Sept 2015 - Mar 2016

Project Collaboration

- Designed, coded, tested, and documented the Language Identification System for Indian languages
- Collaborated with the team to ensure timely and high-quality project completion Technologies Used: Python, NLTK

EDUCATION

National Institute of Technology, Tiruchirappalli

2017 - 2019

Master of Technology in Computer Science

CGPA: 8.08/10

Sinhgad Academy of Engineering, Pune (University of Pune)

2012 - 2016

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Engineering

Percentage: 60.49%

MES' Abasaheb Garware College (AGC) Pune

2010 - 2012

Higher Secondary Education

Percentage: 79.00%

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Secured second prize in Tesco Graduate Hackathon 2019
- Got recognized multiple times in the Team for collaboration and on-time delivery of Projects
- Published a paper titled "Language Identification System for Indian Languages" in the International Journal for Scientific Research & Development (IJSRD)
- Secured second prize in 6th National Project Competition 2016 held at SKNCOE, Pune in Artificial Intelligence